<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Logs on Stephen Malina</title>
    <link>https://an1lam.github.io/log/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Logs on Stephen Malina</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://an1lam.github.io/log/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Daily - 2019-07-16</title>
      <link>https://an1lam.github.io/log/2019-07-16/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://an1lam.github.io/log/2019-07-16/</guid>
      <description>Fell off the log wagon for a few days but I&amp;rsquo;m back. Last few days have been pretty good, although tiredness reduced my productivity per time unit yesterday.
Today went through three more Calculus lectures and their corresponding worked examples, except for maybe one, leaving me in a good position to hopefully get through most or all of another problem set tomorrow.
Also made decent progress on the Probability book. I am a little frustrated with it in comparison to Linear Algebra Done Right in terms of how it presents new concepts and what I perceive as carelessness in its proofs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daily - 2019-07-11</title>
      <link>https://an1lam.github.io/log/2019-07-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://an1lam.github.io/log/2019-07-11/</guid>
      <description>Post-Lunch So far, much more productive than yesterday, finished Problem Set #2 and went through the Exam 1 review lecture for Calculus. Currently debating whether I should take the exam today or wait until tomorrow. I&amp;rsquo;d like to do some probability, but also want to make sure I&amp;rsquo;m making adequate progress, in particular while my motivation&amp;rsquo;s still relatively high.
In the afternoon, I&amp;rsquo;m going to try to finish the probability exercises from Section 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daily - 2019-07-10</title>
      <link>https://an1lam.github.io/log/2019-07-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://an1lam.github.io/log/2019-07-10/</guid>
      <description>Not nearly as productive as yesterday. Spent a bunch of time reading about synthetic biology in the morning rather than doing Calculus.
Had a good session learning about probability. Was referred to Terry Tao&amp;rsquo;s notes on rigorous probability theory as a supplement to the book I&amp;rsquo;m reading. Feeling excited about diving into them.
Got around half-way through Calculus Problem Set #2, hoping to finish tomorrow and maybe get in 1-2 lectures.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>