<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>biology on Stephen Malina</title>
    <link>https://stephenmalina.com/tags/biology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in biology on Stephen Malina</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://stephenmalina.com/tags/biology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Continuous glucose monitors (CGM) and Beyond: A dialogue</title>
      <link>https://stephenmalina.com/post/2023-08-13-cgm-and-beyond/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stephenmalina.com/post/2023-08-13-cgm-and-beyond/</guid>
      <description>What are continuous glucose monitors good for? More broadly, what are continuous measures of physiology (CxM) good for?
Similar to my Elliot and I&amp;rsquo;s dialogue, this post has an unconventional format. It&amp;rsquo;s both a synthesis of Willy&amp;rsquo;s, Eryney&amp;rsquo;s, and my opinions on continuous monitoring combined with a debate in places where we disagree. To try and make it clear which views are coming from each person, we&amp;rsquo;ve annotated sections that come from a subset of us rather than all of us with e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are the bottlenecks to safe, repeatable edits in humans? Part 1</title>
      <link>https://stephenmalina.com/post/2023-06-07-editing-part-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stephenmalina.com/post/2023-06-07-editing-part-i/</guid>
      <description>Summary # Gene editing has made a lot of progress over the past few decades. CRISPR-Cas9 sparked the recent fervor and won some of its early pioneers a Nobel Prize, and more recently Prime Editing and Cytosine/Adenine Base Editors (CBEs/ABEs) have further expanded the range of editing targets and types of edits that are possible while increasing efficiency and reducing the rate of off-target effects.
From the perspective of safe, ubiquitous editing in humans using these systems, a few major challenges for editing remain towards translating novel target discovery into clinical application:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
